<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An oration to the most illustrious and mightie prince Frederick King of Bohemia. Made by Martin Opitius of Silesia. Translated out of Latin</title>
            <title>Oratio ad serenissimum ac potentissimum principem Fridericum, Regem Bohemiæ. English</title>
            <author>Opitz, Martin, 1597-1639.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1620</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 32 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A08514</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 18831</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S121204</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99856389</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99856389</idno>
            <idno type="VID">21932</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A08514)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 21932)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 997:15)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An oration to the most illustrious and mightie prince Frederick King of Bohemia. Made by Martin Opitius of Silesia. Translated out of Latin</title>
                  <title>Oratio ad serenissimum ac potentissimum principem Fridericum, Regem Bohemiæ. English</title>
                  <author>Opitz, Martin, 1597-1639.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[24] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>S.n.],</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>[London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>M.D.C.XX. [1620]</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>A translation of: Oratio ad serenissimum ac potentissimum principem Fridericum, Regem Bohemiæ.</note>
                  <note>Place of publication from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-C⁴.</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in Harvard University. Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Frederick --  I, --  King of Bohemia, 1596-1632.</term>
               <term>Bohemia (Czech Republic) --  History --  1618-1848 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:21932:1"/>
            <p>AN ORATION TO THE MOST ILLVS<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TRIOVS AND MIGHTIE <hi>PRINCE</hi> FREDERICK <hi>King of</hi> Bohemia.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Made by</hi> Martin Opitius <hi>of</hi> SILESIA.</p>
            <p>Tranſlated out of the Latin.</p>
            <p>M. D. C. XX.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="speech">
            <pb facs="tcp:21932:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:21932:2"/>
            <head>An <hi>ORATION</hi> to <hi>Frederick</hi> King of <hi>BOHEMIA.</hi>
            </head>
            <p>
               <seg rend="decorInit">A</seg>LTHOVGH, moſt Illuſtrious <hi>King,</hi> this your hoped and happie entrance into theſe Kingdomes deſerue alſo to be celebrated with the publique ioye of the whole Chriſtian World: Yet wee thinke that wee eſpecially, whome you haue ſo graciouſly receiued into your boſome, can-not without exceeding ſinne bee ſilent. Neither doe I thinke that there is any among vs of ſo deſperate ill na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, ſo auerſe from the loue of Peace, and ſuch an enemy to the ſafetie of his Country, which doth not impute this your ſo much wiſhed Ele<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ction vnto <hi>Heauen;</hi> and withall acknowledge with gratefull mind this great Worke of <hi>God.</hi> Surely your excellent and admired Vertues, the voyces of the greateſt part of the <hi>Empire,</hi> the Alliance and Friendſhip of ſo many great and potent Kings and Princes, and a certaine fatall inclination and affection of theſe Countries towards you, may ſeeme to haue exalted you vnto this height. Yet were there not a few, who well weighing the miſerable condition of our
<pb facs="tcp:21932:3"/>
deplored State did verily beleeue, that you would haue auoyded this enuious Honor. Now the Almightie <hi>Vmpier,</hi> who hath the hearts of Kings in his hand, hath directed your Royall mind, otherwiſe inclinable enough vnto Cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mencie, and hath put vs afflicted Orphans vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der the wing of your protection, and choſen you to bee a Tutour and Parent vnto vs. And whether euer <hi>Guardian</hi> was more glorious, I cannot ſay; yet ſure I am, this Age affoords none more worthy and gracious. For whether wee look vp to your moſt ancie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t Family, or your moſt honorable life, we ſhall find for the firſt, that all Hiſtories, all Monuments of Chronicles doe record the ſplendour of your moſt glorious Houſe; and for the ſecond, the euer-liuing God hath treaſured vp in you ſo many Vertues, that vnleſſe ſo Royall a Stock did claime your birth; with your very Vertues alone, might you merit Scepters and equall <hi>Empires.</hi> Courteſie com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands ſome one, but Maieſty and grauity doth forſake him: Some one man is glorious in the Gowne of <hi>Peace,</hi> but doth not ſo decently weare the Caſſocke of Warre. Another extols Integrity abroad, but he ſtabs it at home in the ſhade of pleaſure. In a word, the World neuer yeelded any man, in whoſe manners was not imprinted ſome ſtep of ſtaine, ſome blaine and blemiſh. Bnt in you, I ſpeake freely without par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiall affection, your veryeſt Enemies cannot pick out any thing to pick a quarrell withall.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21932:3"/>The whole courſe of your life, moſt renowned King, is a Mirrour of Innocencie, and I may more eaſily expreſſe what all Vertue is, then what yours is. None will detract from you the praiſe of <hi>Piety,</hi> but he that is impious; which <hi>Piety</hi> alone hath conquered your minde other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe vnconquerable, and by the which you are ſo conſpicuous aboue all other <hi>Princes,</hi> as it is aboue all other Vertues. The loue of Religion, withoutwhich no man euer grew great, hath bin paſſed ouer vnto you from your Anceftors, with your Inheritance; the Vindication whereof hath bin the proper work of your Family, and whoſe ſuccour, ſeat, and fortreſſe is your <hi>Heidelberge,</hi> an Vniuerſity moſt famous, aſwell for foſtering you, as it. What ſhall I ſpeake of your <hi>Prudence</hi> the <hi>Empreſſe</hi> of humane actions, in which you doe farre ouer-goe the capacity of your yeares? Where is he that excels you in the wiſe ordring of things preſent, in the prudent prouiding for the future, and faithfull remembring of things paſt? Who is more wary to auoyd fraudes, and perils? who more circumſpect in his counſels: In length of life you doe yet come ſhort of middle Age, in depth of iudgement you goe beyond the ancient. In age you profit leiſurely as wee doe, but you poſt before vs in Verue. You are not yet come to ripenes of age, and yet you are full ripe for <hi>Empire.</hi> The fewneſſe of your yeares, moſt prudent King, hath hither to excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed the infirmity of your wiſdome: Now be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides
<pb facs="tcp:21932:4"/>
your diuine towardneſſe (which admits no mediocritie of noble diſpoſition) what ſhall defend your youth? how hard a thing is it in your age to keepe within the compaſſe of your fortune? yet haue you kept within true com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>paſſe. And hereof haue you lately giuen ſo much the more notable proofe, by how much it is more magnificent to ſue to bee eaſed of a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome offered, then to inuade it being denyed. And now ſithence you haue taken it vpon you, what cauſe haue wee to doubt but that you will defend it with the ſame moderation, by the which you did refuſe it? So high and generous a diſpoſition cannot bee vnlike it ſelfe. But, O good God, how doth your gentleneſſe euen ſhine out of your Eyes? You are a ſecond <hi>Tra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ian.</hi> None euer went out of your preſence ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der then he came; none that doth feele your Iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtice doth complaine of crueltie or rigour: yea, you are another <hi>Auguſtus,</hi> whom men may per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceiue to endure puniſhment himſelfe, when hee doth impoſe it vpon others. Nothing (moſt cle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment <hi>Prince</hi>) hath purchaſed greater prayſe to your fortune, then that you are able; nothing hath brought more Honor to your nature, then that you are willing to ſaue all you may. Hold on, O <hi>King,</hi> to winne and weare the moſt glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious Crowne, <hi>Ob Ciues Seruatos,</hi> for ſauing your Countrey. Go on in Gods Name with this your glory, which as it is rarer in a royal Houſe; ſo will it bee more eminent in yours. I want a
<pb facs="tcp:21932:4"/>
new Name, by which I may expreſſe the vnwon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted Modeſty of your Maieſtie. How eaſie is the acceſſe of euery one vnto your Maieſtie, how ioyfull his departure! They come to a <hi>Prince,</hi> and they find a Father; and when they doe with good confidence preſent their Petitions and Complaints before you, they end not their ſpeech, out of your loathing to heare any lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger; but out of their owne baſhfulneſſe to ſpeake any more. So maruellous is your mildeneſſe, ſo courteous your diſpoſition, that you bind men vnto you againſt their wils. Your very Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance ſo cleare with an heroicall cheerfulneſſe, what extraordinary mildneſſe doth it promiſe! And yet your lenitie doth not leſſen your au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority, nor your ſeuerity loſe your loue. There is nothing in you proud, there is nothing inſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent; All your ſtate, gate, motion is amiable; you refreſh both the mindes and eyes of the behol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders. O modeſt King! O lowly Prince! Or ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther high and farre exceeding all height of mor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>talitie! For neuer doe you riſe higher, then when you doe thus depreſſe your ſelfe. What<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer hath weight in it ſelfe doth ſettle it ſelfe below; but an emptie minde is puffed vp with euery little blaſt. And ſurely all theſe things are truely great: And yet no leſſe are thoſe other things by which you haue attayned vnto theſe: I meane, your admirable honeſt behauiour of life, contempt of pleaſures, and diuine Temperance aboue the diſpoſition of your age. Let others
<pb facs="tcp:21932:5"/>
ſhew the Libertie of their power in their licence of ſinning; Let them wallow in adulterous em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bracings; paſſe ouer the nights in Laſciuiouſnes, and their dayes in Gluttony: You are wholy Sobriety and Continence. Needes muſt theſe vertues be in the height of excellence, that doe iſſue from a Fountaine ſo cleere, ſo mudleſſe &amp; ſo pure. To theſe may bee added your ardent loue to Learning and Knowledge; which how much you doe eſteeme, ſo many learned men a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout you doe abundantly teſtifie. That I ſay no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of that Sanctuarie of Learning, your Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brarie of admired greatneſſe, which you are not onely content to maintayne, but doe alſo as a new <hi>Philadelphus</hi> daily adde vnto it, and a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dorne it. Neither doe I touch your skill in di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uers Languages, diuers of which you ſpeake with that facility, that euery on ſeems to be your Natiue Tongue. Herein you are farre more for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunate then <hi>Alexander,</hi> who when hee had ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dued ſo many Nations, did ſcarce vnderſtand the Tongue of any one of them. And let theſe ſuffice as a ſmall taſte taken out of the infinite ranke of your Vertues; wee will leaue the true commendation of them to ſuch whoſe abilitie and aſſuredneſſe in ſpeaking is bounded within the ſame limits with your eternall praiſe; which praiſe if Marbles and Books were not too hard, your ſelfe haue engrauen with the golden Che<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſill of Loue, in the moſt inward affections of your Countrymen.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21932:5"/>Theſe Eies of mine are witneſſes how old and young, men aſwell as women, followed you, departing from them out of your <hi>Pallatinate</hi> with a ſad gladneſſe: In ſuch ſtrange manner did the publike ſafetie and priuate Orbitie ſet ioy and ſorrow to fight together with diuers af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections. One would haue thought that euery man in the Countrey had beene depriued of his Parent. You were not yet gone away, moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſired <hi>Prince,</hi> and yet we did deſire your return. <hi>Neckar</hi> the gentleſt of all Riuers ſeemed, as in times paſt to the <hi>Romans,</hi> ſo now to it ſelfe, bar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>barous. Euen this Heroick Seate of thine, theſe Temples, theſe Towers followed after their Sun in a mournfull manner. That I ſpeake not of men whoſe infinite multitude powred out it ſelfe in euery place, where you came, in the very vaſt Wilderneſſe: and yet euery one thought himſelf to be ſorſaken when you left them: ſighes and teares ſtroue to breake out in abundance. And whereas in bodie, not very many of thoſe multitudes did follow you, yet all with heart and prayers (for otherwiſe they might not) did attend you, departing from them. And did not your Wife the <hi>Heire</hi> of the Name and Vertues of that euer renowned <hi>Queene</hi> great <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> ſeeme now againe to her ſelfe to leaue <hi>Brittaine;</hi> onely glad in this, that it was with you? How had Redneſſe, the Painter of cheekes, dyed her face more then ordinary Milke white! how had a pious ſhower of teares violated her eyes, clee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rer
<pb facs="tcp:21932:6"/>
then the Stars, ſhining wi thout the Moone! ſighes gaue the farewell, becauſe words ſufficed not. And for your ſelfe I cannot ſay whether greater <hi>Piety</hi> perſwaded your ſtay or your iour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ney. You left your <hi>Mother</hi> that <hi>Princeſſe</hi> of higheſt birth, who is yet higher then her birth, for that ſhee hath borne you. You left your chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, that is to ſay, a great part of your heart; you left your Subiects, euery of which could wiſh to liue and die with you. You went from peace to Warre, from Acquaintance to Stran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gers; from the moſt peaceable Shore of <hi>Rheine,</hi> to <hi>Mulda,</hi> whoſe ſtreames were ſwelled with the bloud of the Inhabitants; from Vineyards and a Garden of admirable beautie, to Fields ſtay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned with the Robberies of ſauage Murtherers, and couered with the carkaſſes of the ſlaine; from a moſt pleaſant Caſtle, to a vaſt, yet deſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>late and deſpoyled Place. An vnhappy change; ſaue that thereby you bring with you ſplendor to the Place; a perpetuall ſpring to the Fields; tranquillitie to <hi>Mulda,</hi> a friend to ſtrangers; and peace to men in Armes. You come then in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to this <hi>Scene,</hi> into this moſt intricate Tragedie, as a very <hi>God</hi> out of the Engine. <hi>Pietie hath o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercome this bard iourney;</hi> the loue of vs hath ouercome the ſharpe and high Mountaines of <hi>Bohemia;</hi> within which Nature hath entren<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ched it: Your Clemencie hath ouercome the Inclemencie of the place with much better luck then <hi>Hannibal,</hi> the braueſt of Commanders; who
<pb facs="tcp:21932:6"/>
in old time paſſed his Armie ouer the tops of the high <hi>Alpes,</hi> thorough the Cloudes that ſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med to touch <hi>Heauen.</hi> For at the ſight of him all <hi>Italie</hi> trembled, as at the falling of a Thunder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bolt: But by your comming the Tempeſt is ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peaſed, the winde are layed, all things are be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come calme and cleare. Hee brought with him Troupes of Souldiers, that he might cut vp the <hi>Romans:</hi> but you come attended with Troups for our preſeruation. He had ſharpned his Sword againſt the Citie; but your back doth blunt the Swords of our Enemies. Sauage and ſworne hatred opened the way to him; but incredible loue laies it open to you. He ſeemed to be borne to the murder of men and the waſting of Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties; but you are borne to the infinite good of the Common-wealth. His approch to the gates rayſed feare and horrour: You, they would be glad to beare in their very eyes, into the Throne of ſo many <hi>Emperers</hi> and <hi>Kings.</hi> Him, the feare<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>full Mothers Children, Virgines, women and men ranne away from; You they come out to meet in Triumph. His preſence all did deteſt with mourning and pittifull yellings; yours they doe celebrate with gladneſſe and great reioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing. They that haue ouer-liued their former ſorrow, are now ſcarce able to beare their pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent ioy. I doe alſo verily beleeue that if there be left in dead men any ſence of things on earth, that the ghoſts of thoſe men that haue ſacrifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced their heart bloud to the publique libertie,
<pb facs="tcp:21932:7"/>
are now repleniſhed with vnſpeakable ioy; and doe thinke that they haue ſpent their liues to good purpoſe.</p>
            <p>O braue <hi>King,</hi> this is not enough, O <hi>King,</hi> worthy of the <hi>Empire</hi> of the whole World, worthy of the fauour; worthy alſo of the admi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration of thy very Enemies! O thou pious <hi>Prince,</hi> whom not our felicitie and proſperitie, but the hardneſſe of our fortune, &amp; the wounds engrauen in our bodies with the Swords of our Enemies, hath ſollicited to accept our <hi>Diadem!</hi> O moſt happy you, not becauſe you haue alrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy ſubdued the whole furie of our Enemies, but becauſe you ſeeme to deſerue happineſſe for vs all. O happy day that brought you forth into the World, and firſt deſigned you vnto this Kingdome. Which birth day of ſo great a <hi>Prince</hi> beginnes to bee vnto vs alſo another birth day, which hath brough forth ſo diuine a Manſion for Vertue, and did alſo conſecrate it, to the whole Chriſtian World. <hi>All Haile, O Lord:</hi> For we haue not caſt off Rule; but out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rage and crueltie ruling ouer vs. Wee can well enough obey, but we cannot beare <hi>Tyranny;</hi> we will ſerue thee, that we may be freed. <hi>All haile, O King, all haile, O Father of our Countrey, All haile thou Darling and Minion of Mankind. For thee, O Illuſtrious Honour of our Age,</hi> for thy ſafetie doe we pray; for vnder thy Gouernment are wee ſecure of our owne ſafetie. <hi>God</hi> grant vnto thee that by thy hand our tottering State
<pb facs="tcp:21932:7"/>
may be vnderpropped and reſtored; that thou mayeſt be partaker of that Vow which <hi>Octauius</hi> did once ſo much deſire, that thou mayeſt truly be ſtyled, <hi>Optimi Status Auctor: The Founder of a moſt happle State.</hi> And let late olde Age draw in the ſwelling Sailes of thy glorious Reigne, which in your Youth you haue now hoyſed vp to ſo fauourable a wind. And beare away with you this hope, when by death you ſhall leaue vs: That the happy foundations, which you haue layed, ſhall abide for euer in their proper place.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>God ſaue thee, O Queene Daughter of that moſt Illuſtrious Heros,</hi> whoſe Prayſes cannot bee pent vp in the Straits of this Age, who hath ioy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned profound Learning to incredible Wiſdom of gouerning; who vnder a happie Starre hath added <hi>England</hi> vnto <hi>Scotland. God ſaue thee O Wife of this Prince,</hi> who doth now couple our Kingdomes to his owne Countrey with like glorie, &amp; I would to God it may be with equall fortune. <hi>God</hi> bleſſe you both, who are by con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent of <hi>God</hi> and man a moſt choice paire. <hi>All haile</hi> to you <hi>Sunne</hi> and <hi>Moone.</hi> How ſweet a ſight is it to our Citizens to ſee what a Lord, to our Souldiers to ſee what a Leader they haue with vniuerſall conſent elected, and with ſuch longing deſire expected? How pleaſant, <hi>O King,</hi> is it to vs to heare theſe words out of thy bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed mouth? That this Acceptance of the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome proceeded from the loue of <hi>Peace,</hi> and
<pb facs="tcp:21932:8"/>
not of <hi>Empire:</hi> that you are drawne into theſe ſtirres by our miſerie, and not carryed by your owne diſpoſition; that the Modeſtie of your refuſing was ouercome by the obſtinacie of our offering. That you haue preferred the publique Securitie before your owne priuate eaſe. That it is but a ſmall matter to deſire a people, but not ſo eaſie to defend them. And that it is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt better to let goe an Empire that is in right ones owne, then to purchaſe a new one with the bloud of the Citizens: But now, ſith this Scepter can neither be poſſeſt nor forſaken with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out perill, that now our eſtate and condition is your owne; and that therefore you will now vſe your beſt endeauour that wee ſhould not neede to deſire another King while <hi>God</hi> ſhall giue you life.</p>
            <p>We know, we know very well, moſt gracious <hi>Prince,</hi> that you did vnwillingly enter vpon this Kingdome which was vnwillingly left. We alſo were compelled; we came not of our own accord to implore your fortitude and defence: who were not ignorant of your Clemencie. We call <hi>God</hi> and men to witneſſe that by compulſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on we tooke vp Armes to defend the ſafetie of our Countrey, and that Liberty which is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lowed to the beſeſt Nations; and laſtly our Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion which is to be preferred before all other Cauſes, and whoſe name was in time paſt ſo ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred among the very <hi>Gentiles,</hi> that at the time that the <hi>French</hi> were ſpoyling <hi>Rome, Lu. Albu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nius</hi>
               <pb facs="tcp:21932:8"/>
one of the common people, putting out of his Cart his Wife and Children, tooke vp into it, the <hi>Veſtall Virgines</hi> which did follow vpon their bare feet the ſacred things which fled from the furie of their Enemies. So much at that time in the meaneſt men did publique <hi>Religion</hi> excell priuate affections.</p>
            <p>To be aſſailed in body and eſtate is grieuous: but in Conſcience, is intollerable.</p>
            <p>And ſuch we ſee is the nature of Liberty, that no good man will loſe it but with his life. As courage and ſtrength vſes to increaſe to wilde beaſts broke out of their Dennes, and doth be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>come in a maner double: So is it with our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; it could no longer diſſemble their manly courage, the due prayſe of which none could euer depriue vs of, when beſides the iuſt hatred it bore to cruell counſels and practiſes againſt vs, it burnt in deſire of regaining the Libertie of the Countrey deſperately loſt and oppreſſed. Which it is alwayes lawfull for them to repur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chaſe who by nature were borne to liue free, and had alſo their Libertie eſtabliſhed vnto them by the fundamentall Lawes and Priuiledges of the Kingdome, confirmed vnto them with the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Bond of Othes, and ratified by the Char<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ters and great Seales of Kings and Emperours. Wee doe very well know that the prayſe of o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bedience is enough in Subiects; that good <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces</hi> are to be wiſhed for; that euill, (if they fall to their lot) are to bee endured. But theſe things
<pb facs="tcp:21932:9"/>
doe in no ſort concerne vs, this is not our Caſe. We, wee haue taken vp<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Armes after incredible Patience; not with any mind of rebelling, but at the Exigence of extreme Neceſſitie: Not in a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny priuate Conſpiracie of ſome few, but with the vniuerſall and ioynt conſent of the whole State; not in any contempt of Magiſtracie, but in defiance of moſt damnable practize againſt our Liues, Libertie and Religion: Neither did we doe this againſt a lawfull King, but to eſcape the deuilliſh deceits of bloudie Murtherers, who doe openly profeſle that no Faith is to be kept, whereby we haue receiued vnvaluable damage: who gaine time, and coozen well-meaning peo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple by Periurie, as Cheaters doe Children with falſe Dice and Cards: We haue now at length learned to diſtruſt, being taught by too many wofull Examples. Wee know very well what horrible Thunderbolts are darted from the <hi>Tar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peian Rock</hi> at <hi>Rome.</hi> And that <hi>Romes Iupiter</hi> can by the way transferre Principalities and King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>domes from whom and to whom he pleaſe, like the Deuill his Maſter: <hi>All this will I giue thee if thou wilt fall downe and worſhip me.</hi> And that he doth damme ſoules to Hell for his Recreation, and to make his <hi>Holineſſe</hi> ſport. Who knowes not how ſmall protection <hi>Hus</hi> a Citizen of this Kingdome found in the ſafe conduct of <hi>Caeſar?</hi> No leſſe Tempeſt had ouer-taken <hi>Luther</hi> at <hi>Wormes,</hi> had not the braue <hi>Emperour</hi> put on a reſolution neuer to ſtampe ſuch a ſtaine vpon
<pb facs="tcp:21932:9"/>
his honourable Name: Had not <hi>Lewis</hi> alſo, the moſt clement <hi>Prince</hi> of your <hi>Progenitors,</hi> with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtood the <hi>Romiſh</hi> diſhonourable determination to breake faith.</p>
            <p>By the very like Game and foule Play ſhould we haue bin coozened, and in the like Trap did<note place="margin">Ieſuites.</note> theſe men endeuour to haue caught vs, who doe vſually inuade Lords of Nations with Poniards and Parricidiall Arts; which grow remarkable in the World and glorious Martyrs at <hi>Rome</hi> by the bloud and murther of Kings; who by ſuper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>latiue horrible wickedneſſe did deſtroy great <hi>Henry</hi> of <hi>France,</hi> that Thunderbolt of Warre; ſubiecting him (whom the huge weight of his whole Countrey, when he ſtood vnder it, could not moue,) to the butcherie of one deſperate Villaine: who did their beſt to haue daſht to the wals of his Kingdome with fire and Gun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powder, your <hi>Father-in-Law,</hi> the matchleſſe <hi>Monarch of great Britaine:</hi> who haue perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded themſelues and others, that <hi>Saluation of Soules</hi> conſiſts in Murders of Kings and waſting of <hi>Kingdomes;</hi> who make it but ſport and play to murther the poore, to condemne the inno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cent, to take away mens liues, with Rack, Fire, and Sword, and (becauſe they will ſpare to ſpill mens bloud) to bury men aliue; and to iumble all Diuine and Humane things together. Theſe men firſt crept into the Courts, after into the Conſciences of our Gouernours: Theſe were the Directors and Preſidents of all the Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels:
<pb facs="tcp:21932:10"/>
Theſe mingled with them fraudes, diſſimu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lations, perfidy, without which they teach that none can rule well. Theſe theeuiſh Mates and masked Murtherers were of late continually whiſpering into the eares of our Magiſtrates a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt vs that common Sentence of their Sect, <hi>Vre, Seca, Burne, Cut off.</hi> With the Lyes and craftie Conueyances of theſe fellowes, as with excellent Arts, were wee gouerned. Vnto theſe alſo were adioyned ſome <hi>Seians,</hi> euill and peſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Counſellors, who itching with Ambition and Luſt of <hi>Eminence,</hi> thought no kind of per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidie againſt vs too much. And hence was it that our Churches were abuſed and ſhut vp; Our Priuiledges violated; the innocent clapt vp in Priſon and many wayes fined and puniſhed: All acceſſe to our Princes ſhut vp againſt vs, the De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>crees of <hi>Rodulph</hi> the Emperour eluded, and ſhifted off. Of men, that were contrary minded to them, ſome were aſſailed by threatnings; ſome corrupted with Dignities and Rewards: All right of Nations vvas broken: the Co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth was ouer-flowne with an inundation of wickedneſſe, and Religion was diſturbed with maruailous Treacheries. We intreated, we be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſought, we wept, we were inſtant in petitioning without any licence to depart, and vpheld our labour without hope of eaſe and redreſſe. But all in vaine! wee were any where ſafer then at home; and we got nothing, by our vaine pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers, but onely tyring of our ſelues with intrea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting, and of them with hearing.</p>
            <p>
               <pb facs="tcp:21932:10"/>When then wee preuailed nothing by this milde courſe, but ſaw that heauier burdens were daily impoſed vpon vs, as on ſuch who by cu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtome of bearing were growne to beare them with more eaſe; all the matter and fuell of our <hi>Patience</hi> being ſpent, we did perfunctorily re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehend ſome of them. Hence came the kind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling of thoſe Firebrands of Warre which the diſturbers of <hi>Peace</hi> had ſo long deſired and ſought: Hence were <hi>Ianus</hi> his gates of Warre opened: Hence was it that all things were defi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led with burning, with Carcaſſes of the ſlaine, with horrour and bloud: or, as they pleaſe to terme it, corrected, I wys, and amended. I tre<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to relate the ſauage immanity committed by the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, ſuch as Barbariſme neuer hard of, &amp; which perhaps ſhall not find credit hereafter with Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſterity. Neither could the crying of Infants, the ſobbing of Children, the teares of Matrones, or the gray haires of the old men, any whit mooue theſe out-ragious and ſauage beaſts. Virgins were abuſed in common, ſtrong and weake were killed together; the Fields were waſted; the Wealth and Strength of the Kingdome was worne out; and what the Sword had left, was conſumed with fire. Hitherto haue wee recko<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned vp things to be bewayled with ſorrow; now I muſt come to relate things, that are to be blu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed at for ſhame: How a Mother hurles her Children into the Riuer and drownes them, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they ſhall not bee hewed in pieces before
<pb facs="tcp:21932:11"/>
her face with the Swords of the Murtherers. The bodies of the dead are pulled out of their Graues in the middeſt of the Church: The dead bodies of Women lately buried (let Chriſtians ſhake for horror) vvere layd naked vpon the Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tars, tyed by the hands and feet, and ſet vpright vvith proppes to ſtay them at the doores of the Churches. And many other things, vvith as much abominable out-rage, were perpetrated. O Age more ingenious then <hi>Mezentius</hi> his, <hi>Ti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>berius</hi> his, <hi>Neroes, Domitians,</hi> and other Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Men to deuiſe Crueltie! Our liue men ſuffice not to theſe ſhames of Mankinde to act their abominable barbarouſneſſe vpon; the dead muſt be pulled out of their Graues to endure their villanie. We thus prouoked with their vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpeakable villanies doe then firſt flye to Warre; and then doe vvee let them know that vvee can fight for our Countrey; and that vvee that had ceaſed to feare them, did beginne to hate them. That theſe things freed vs from our Oath to the King none vvill deny, but ſuch as are altogether ignorant of the Rights and Priuiledges of this Kingdome. Men vvill rather laugh at our Leni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie; and all men fret at our folly, vvho haue ſo long digeſted ſuch intollerable out-rage.</p>
            <p>Novv doe we, not vvithout heauenly inſtinct and inſpiration, retyre our ſelues into the bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſome of thy Clemencie, vvhoſe very * Name<note place="margin">
                  <hi>Frederick</hi> which ſignifies <hi>Rich Peace,</hi> or <hi>Rich</hi> in <hi>Peace.</hi>
               </note> doth novv promiſe <hi>Peace</hi> vnto vs. <hi>God</hi> be mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifull vnto thee, moſt louing <hi>Prince,</hi> and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vvard
<pb facs="tcp:21932:11"/>
this thine extraordinarie gentlenes vnto vs: We will ſhew our thankfulneſſe vnto thee in Seruice and Obſeruance, if we can do no more. He that hereafter cals vs <hi>Bohemians, Morauians, Sileſians, Luſatians,</hi> ſhall ſay much; but more if he call vs thine; we are thine while we are. And to goe away and dye for thee whenſoeuer <hi>God</hi> pleaſe, we wlll eſteeme it a happy ſigne. They ſay that the <hi>Sardi</hi> by taking the iuyce of a certaine Herbe doe laugh at their paſſage out of life. For you, deare <hi>Prince,</hi> we will willingly and chear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully goe out to meete Death it ſelfe if need re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire. We long to fight for you; We ſhall want no courage that fight vnder ſo valiant a <hi>Prince,</hi> no will vnder ſo vndaunted a Captain, no good ſucceſſe vnder ſo iuſt a <hi>King:</hi> We ſhall haue the better in Armes that haue the better Cauſe. It ſhal not be our wearines but the death of our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nemies, that ſhal put an end to our purſuit. And our Armes, that we tooke vp ſo ſlowly, wee will lay downe as leiſurely. If our number bee leſſe, our courage ſhall bee greater: They are neuer many which be ſlaine with the Sword.</p>
            <p>In the meane time, wee haue a Suite to thee, <hi>O Prage,</hi> which art the Nurſe and Hoſteſſe of ſo many <hi>Emperours</hi> and <hi>Kings,</hi> that thou vvilt no longer detaine this beſt <hi>Prince</hi> from our <hi>Si<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſia,</hi> vvhich without queſtion doth euen now earneſtly expect, and ardently deſire to ſee his face. Enter into our Countrey <hi>O King,</hi> enter; Thou ſhalt come moſt welcome vnto all, who
<pb facs="tcp:21932:12"/>
commeſt for the good of all. Enter enuironed with Guards and Armies; vvee vvill neuer be a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fraid of them, vvho haue learned to liue vnder ſo modeſt and iuſt a <hi>King.</hi> Enter vvithout them, if you pleaſe: heere ſhall you finde your owne people your owne Seruants. Surely, me thinks, I ſee that moſt pleaſant Countrey vvholy riſing vp and comming to meet thee. Me thinkes I be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold the great affection, of the <hi>Princes,</hi> the e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mulation of the Nobles, the Aſſemblies of <hi>Se<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natours,</hi> and thoſe innumerable multitudes of people powred out to behold you; ſome going before, ſome going by, ſome following after, all eagerly preſſing to enioy your preſence; and the vvals of the faireſt Citie <hi>Vratiſlauia,</hi> receiuing with long-vviſhed embracings their ſo much deſired <hi>Prince,</hi> and the tops of the higheſt Tur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rets, as it were, bending dovvne themſelues to do you Honour; and the Citie not a little proud that it hath the Honour to entertayne thy Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ieſty. But all theſe things I leaue to the Learned, vvhereof vve haue very great plentie: And vvell knovving and vveighing both your greatneſſe, moſt mightie <hi>King,</hi> and the vveakneſſe of mine ovvne vvit, I vvill reuerence thy heauenly Ver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tues vvith admiration onely and ſilence.</p>
            <p>Novv let vs all vvith publike voyce humbly beſeech the Lord of all, vvhich alters the times and courſes of times, which puls downe and ſets vp <hi>Kings,</hi> that <hi>Hee</hi> would keepe, preſerue and protect thy Maieſtie, &amp; gouerne thy Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels
<pb facs="tcp:21932:12"/>
and Cogitations. Long and much may <hi>Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligion</hi> flouriſh vnder thee, and let it receiue in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>creaſe and credit from thy <hi>Pietie.</hi> Let bee roo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted vp all ſtemmes of Superſtition and doting toyes of traditions, abominations before the eyes of God. Let thine Enemies be confounded, and come following thoſe Banners that they came out to meet in the Field: Bee more victo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rious in Battell then that braue <hi>Ziſca,</hi> that rock and terrour of euill men. And excell your ſelfe in Peace, and increaſe that Kingdome gowned, which you haue ſet at Libertie armed. But if thou <hi>O God</hi> doſt prepare ſome heauier croſſe for vs, and wilt not yet, by reaſon of our ſinnes, put an end to our labours, yet grant that for the defence of thy Name, for our <hi>Prince,</hi> for our Libertie, for our Countrey, we may either ouer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>comevaliantly, or dye bleſſedly, or both. Defend his Gouernment that defends thy Glorie, and after Hee hath happily paſſed through a long Race in this mortall life, and ſhall haue layed a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide this moſt happie burthen of the Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, tranſlate him from this mortall Scepter to a Crowne of life which ſhall not bee taken from him for euermore.</p>
            <closer>And let all that loue <hi>Chriſts</hi> Truth, ſay AMEN.</closer>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
